“哎呀，真是感谢工业社会拯救了咱，让我们免于此等水深火热”
Thank you, Industrial Society, for saving us from this,
某条网帖配着瑞士阿尔卑斯山如画美景，反讽地写道
sarcastically declares one internet post, featuring a picturesque view of the Swiss Alps.
以前呐，单靠一个爷们儿的收入，就能养得起郊区的房子
Can you believe people used to afford a suburban home,
车子、三个娃子，还能度假、上大学，你敢信？
a car, three kids, a holiday, and college, all on the income of one guy?
如今这世道是怎么了？
What happened to society?
怀旧党们不禁扼腕叹息
asks the nostalgics.
“拒绝现代，拥抱传统”——密苏里州一位16岁的小年轻
Reject modernity. Embrace tradition, says the 16-year-old teenager in Missouri,
发了张俩人站在电线杆前的照片，并如是说道
posting a picture of two people standing in front of a power line.
“中世纪的农民啊，那闲暇时间和假期可比今天的人多多了”
Medieval peasants had more free time and holidays than people today,
另一则高论获得了足足11万7千个赞
proclaims another, to over 117,000 likes.
嘿，哥们儿，当今世上还有几十亿人
Hey pal, there are billions of people in the world today
过着中世纪农民般的日子呢，他们的工时显然可没比咱们少
who live the lives of medieval peasants, and they clearly don't work fewer hours than we do.
这类论调啊，可谓是当代数字“时代精神”的缩影
This kind of talking point is part of today's digital zeitgeist,
横跨了各种立场和年龄段
from across a spectrum of viewpoints and age groups.
当然，我知道不是所有人都这么想
And I know it's not all people,
大多数人心里清楚，咱这日子是前所未有的好
most people know we've never had it so good.
本视频专供那些真心实意认为“今不如昔”的朋友们“享用”
This video is for the folks who genuinely believe that life was better in the good old days.
那会儿啊，更幸福，更淳朴
Happier, more virtuous.
虽说没那么多花里胡哨的好玩意儿，但一切都那么有条不紊
We didn't have as many nice things, but everything made sense.
无论是衣着、建筑、还是社交礼仪
The outfits, the buildings, the social queues,
人们比现在友善多了，也更虔诚，更受人尊敬
people being more friendly than they used to, people being more religious, more public esteem.
他们的终极结论可能是
Ultimately, they might say,
我们必须回归传统，回归那种相夫教子的保守生活
we must return to tradition, and a domestic, conservative way of living.
而我，只用一句话就能把这些怼回去：你想过那种日子，谁拦着你了？
And I can easily dismiss all of that as bullshit by saying, you can already do that.
你大可以去过田园牧歌的农耕生活，假装自己是个中世纪老农
You can go and live a pastoral farmsteading life and pretend you're a medieval peasant.
毕竟这也不犯法
It's not illegal.
当今社会，就有不少人过着仿佛1950年代，乃至1880年代的生活
There are many people today who live as if it was the 1950s or the 1880s.
你根本不用昭告天下
You don't have to advertise it to the world.
你和阿米什人的区别在于，人家是真刀真枪地在践行
What separates you from the Amish is that they're actually devoted.
他们是真正在过着你声称想要的生活
They actually live the life that you purport to want.
而当他们被要求解释那个逝去的年代究竟好在哪儿时
And when they get asked to explain what made this bygone era so great,
答案总是围绕着人们“没有”什么
it's always about what people didn't have.
仿佛日子就是因为“更糟”才“更好”的
As if things were better because they were worse.
哦，我们那时候没有智能手机
Oh, we didn't always have smartphones.
我们必须和彼此交谈
We had to talk to each other.
我们没有中央供暖
We didn't have central heating.
但我们因此更快乐
And we were happier for it.
不，你他喵的才不快乐
No, you fucking weren't.
50年代的时候，不到一半的英国家庭有浴室
Back in the 50s, less than half of British households had a bathroom.
人们对此深恶痛绝
And people hated it.
有家报纸说，在一个文明国家
With one newspaper saying it was disconcerting
竟有如此多的人只能靠便携式浴盆洗澡，真是闹斯特麻麻了
that so many people in a civilised country were stuck with the bleak alternative of a portable bath.
大多数房子甚至没有室内厕所
Most houses didn't even have an indoor toilet.
厕所远在花园尽头的小棚子里
It was in the shed at the bottom of the garden.
许多人回望那个时代，视其为社会高度统一和家庭价值观的黄金年代
Many people look back on this time as a golden age of social conformity and family values.
后来“大逆不道”的性、世俗和艺术革命毁掉了他们珍视的一切
Before the sexual, secular, artistic revolution ruined everything that was important to them.
另一些人则将其视为“正经工作”的顶峰，工业、高薪、且稳定的高薪
Others look back on it as the high point of real proper jobs, in industry, high wages, secure wages.
而且还有工会罩着
And they were unionised.
贫富差距达到了历史上的最小点
Wealth disparities were at its smallest ever in history.
有时，这种怀旧甚至无关政治
And sometimes it isn't even political.
Facebook上充斥着无数的老登群组
There are countless Facebook groups full of older generations
纪念着上世纪中叶那些平平无奇的琐碎事物
commemorating many of the banal complexities of the mid-century.
从老式转盘电话到垃圾工
Everything from rotary phones to bin men.
哎我真是曹乐，他们竟然连垃圾工都要搞政治正确
Oh, goddammit, they made the bin men woke.
然而，多亏了神奇的历史档案
However, thanks to the wonders of historical archives,
我们得以描绘出一幅1950年代的真实生活画卷
we can paint an accurate picture of normal life in the 1950s,
一幅未经怀旧滤镜和流行文化扭曲的画卷
untainted by nostalgia and distortion by popular culture.
住房
Houses.
没人想住鸽子笼，但1950年代的房子，面积还不到今天房子的一半大
Nobody wants to live in a pod, but houses in the 1950s were less than half as big as houses of today.
看看这个“豪华住宅”的广告
Look at this ad for a luxury home.
按今天的标准来看，也就平平无奇，甚至可以说相当局促
It's pretty average or even quite cramped by today's standards.
虽然那会儿房价肯定更便宜，但你可别想着装修
And while it was certainly cheaper, don't even think about renovating it.
有些房子的浴室墙壁里有特制的空槽
Some houses were built with special caverns in the bathroom walls
你用完的剃须刀片就直接扔进去，然后抛诸脑后
where you would simply dump all your used razors and then forget about them,
把这一堆生锈的刀片留给下一个倒霉蛋去处理
leaving the next person to deal with all those rusty blades.
如果你想砸开那堵墙，我希望你先打好破伤风疫苗
If you want to knock down that wall, I hope you have your tetanus vaccine.
这还是在你买得起“豪华”私宅的前提下
That's even if you could afford the luxury of your own home.
那时的白人贫困率是现在的两倍，至于黑人贫困率嘛……
The white poverty rate was double back then, and the black poverty rate...
你懂的
well, you can already guess.
汽车
Cars.
当时的汽车简直是移动棺材
Cars at the time were death traps.
人们对汽车物理学一知半解
Cars physics were not well understood.
他们天真地以为，只要不断给车增加厚度，车就能“吸收”掉碰撞
They thought if you keep adding bulk to it, the car will just absorb the crash.
结果呢，只是把所有的冲击力，原封不动地转移到了车内脆弱的“肉馅”上
Instead, it just transferred all the impact force into the frail meat puppets inside.
城市
Cities.
直到1970年代环保运动兴起，在街上乱扔垃圾才被视为一种社会禁忌
Littering in the street wasn't seen as socially taboo until the 1970s environmentalist movement.
那时可没有什么空气污染管制，工厂玩命地喷着煤灰和烟尘
There were no regulations on air pollution, so factories spewed out as much coal and smoke dust
像匹兹堡这样的重工业城镇，那是经常不见天日
that it often blocked out the sun in highly industrial towns like Pittsburgh.
又比如伦敦，仅1952年12月的短短四天里
Or in London, where over just four days in December 1952,
大烟雾就夺走了约12000人的生命
smog killed roughly 12,000 people,
并导致10万人严重患病
and made 100,000 seriously ill.
不过，我得给怀旧党们扳回一城
I will give the nostalgists one victory, though.
与今天相比，1950年代的盗窃率和入室盗窃率确实低得惊人
Theft and burglary rates were incredibly low in the 1950s compared to today.
虽然这大概是因为大家都没啥值得偷的东西吧（笑）
Although, that's because nobody had anything worth stealing.
工作
Work.
美国男性平均每年要比现在多工作约300个小时
The average American man worked about 300 more hours per year than today.
而且吭哧吭哧干了半天，也没多拿几个子儿
And he didn't even get paid more for all this toil.
剔除通胀因素后，1957年的工资中位数，甚至略低于今天
Adjusting for inflation, the median salary in 1957 was slightly lower than it is today.
他得7点半才到家，回家揍完老婆就径直上床睡觉了
He isn't getting home until 7:30, and he's going straight to bed after beating his wife.
至于那个“在家貌美如花、在外温顺听话”的妻子形象，也纯属扯淡
The idea of a gorgeous, stay-at-home, submissive wife is a load of nonsense, too.
三分之一的已婚妇女仍然有工作，诚然，这比例是今天的一半
One in three married women still had jobs, which is half the rate it is today, true,
但也绝对是女性中不小的一部分了
but it's certainly a large chunk of women.
而那些被迫沦为家庭主妇的女性，往往觉得这种生活既无聊又空虚
Women who were relegated to being housewives often found it boring and unfulfilling.
我问自己，为何如此不满
I ask myself why I'm so dissatisfied.
我身体健康，孩子可爱，有漂亮的新家，钱也够用
I've got my health, fine children, a lovely new home, enough money.
我丈夫作为电子工程师，前途一片光明
My husband has a real future as an electronics engineer.
他可没有我这些破感受
He doesn't have any of these feelings.
我一觉醒来，对生活毫无期待
I wake up and there's nothing to look forward to.
我试过了所有女人应该做的事
I've tried everything women are supposed to do.
培养爱好、侍弄花园、和邻居们打成一片
Hobbies, gardening, being very social with my neighbors.
我开始觉得自己毫无个性
I begin to feel I have no personality.
我只是个召之即来，挥之即去的工具人
I'm somebody who can be called on when you want something.
但我到底是谁
But who am I?
我好像总是在睡觉
I seem to sleep so much.
我不知道自己为什么总是这么累
I don't know why I should be so tired.
并不是因为干了多少活
It's not the work.
我只觉得，我根本没有在“活着”
I just don't feel alive.
当然，也并非每个人都虔诚又纯洁
Nor was everybody pious and morally pure.
早在1939年，只有少数英国人相信有来生
As early as 1939, a minority of Britons believed in life after death,
这表明，那时的人们可能并不像我们想象的那么宗教化
indicating that maybe people back then weren't as religious as we think.
1950年代的电影总给人一种印象，好像每个人都是品行端正
1950s cinema gives the impression that everyone acted as upstanding
不近女色、满口雅言的模范公民
sexless, clean-mouthed citizens all the time.
但这不过是那些大制片厂的“行业自律”罢了
But that was just voluntary regulation by the big studios.
这边是富丽堂皇的电影院，放着毫无“性”趣的好莱坞浪漫剧
For every grand cinema showing the latest Hollywood romance devoid of sex,
那边就有更多乌烟瘴气的苍蝇馆子，放着低成本、很攒劲的色情片
there were many more seedy dive cinemas showing low-budget, raunchy sexploitation movies.
伦敦的苏豪区，当年可是以成人影院和脱衣舞俱乐部闻名全球的
Soho in London was internationally famous for its adult theatres and strip clubs.
备受争议的性学研究者阿尔弗雷德·金赛
Alfred Kinsey, a controversial sex researcher,
他把和他共事的人也干了，不限男女
在1953年发现，大约一半的白人女性
found in 1953 that around half of white women
和68%的大学白人男学生，在美利坚有过婚前性行为
and 68% of college student white men in America had engaged in premarital intercourse.
至于说脏话，也相当普遍
Swearing, also pretty common.
这儿有一些好莱坞老电影的NG片段，全是演员忘词儿的
Here's some outtakes from old Hollywood films where the actors mess up their lines.
自己练听力吧
这还只是混迹职场的大牌女演员
And that's just the high-profile actresses who were in the workplace.
你大可以想象一下，在日常闲聊中，普罗大众会飙出什么样的脏话
You can imagine the kind of foul-mouthed language used by everyday people in casual settings.
听完这些，怀旧党们可能得把目光放得更远了
Having heard all this, the nostalgic may look back even further.
如果1950年代并不如我想的那么保守
If the 1950s weren't as conservative as I thought,
那，真正的“美好旧时光”一定是在1920年代
well, the true good old days must have been the 1920s,
或者1800年代，再或是中世纪
or the 1800s, the Middle Ages.
但这纯粹是一场比惨大赛
But it's all a race to the bottom,
因为保守派们总是在念叨着
because conservatives have always been talking about
“美好的旧时光”
the good old days.
在1930年代，一家英国报纸报道称
In the 1930s, one English newspaper reported,
“在历史上，没有任何一个时期的年轻人，曾如此旗帜鲜明地
There is no period in history in which young people have given such emphatic utterance
表现出一种抛弃旧事物、渴望新事物的倾向”
to a tendency to project that which is old and wish for that which is new.
另一家报纸则指责道，“父母们自己，常常未能尽到他们最基本的责任
With another blaming, parents themselves having frequently failed in their obvious duty to
即教会自己的孩子自控和纪律”
teach self-control and discipline to their own children.
1939年，一项盖洛普民调显示，高达62%的美国人认为
In 1939, a Gallup poll revealed that 62% of Americans thought that life was better
那个“马车时代”的生活更胜一筹
in the era of horse and boogie.
1890年代的美国，其生活水平堪比当代的马拉维
America in the 1890s had a standard of living comparable to modern day Malawi,
也就是这世界上最穷的国家
the poorest country in the world.
20世纪初，美国和英国的人均预期寿命约为52岁
Life expectancy at the turn of the 20th century was around 52 in the US and UK,
欧洲大陆那边还要再低一点
and a bit lower on the continent.
放眼当今世界，只有两个国家的预期寿命有这么低
There are only two countries in the world today with a life expectancy that low.
尼日利亚和乍得
Nigeria and Chad.
但显然，就连这种日子，对于19世纪的人来说都太“安逸”了
But apparently even this was too cushy for people in the 19th century.
1832年，安德鲁·杰克逊宣称，在他的领导下
In 1832, Andrew Jackson proclaimed that under his leadership,
合众国正在“复兴那种忠贞的爱国主义和妥协精神
the United States was Reviving that devoted patriotism and spirit of compromise
这正是大革命先贤们和我们联邦之父的卓越品质”
which distinguished the sages of the revolution and the fathers of our union.
显然，50年前，也就是1770年代，那个18世纪，日子要更好
Evidently, things were better 50 years ago, in the 1770s, the 18th century.
但即便是在18世纪，人们也在抱怨
But even in the 18th century, people complained that
说那些年轻的贵族，公然违背良善品德
young noblemen who, in direct opposition to good character,
终日沉溺于纸醉金迷、放荡不羁的生活
hurry through life in one invariable round of debauchery.
最后总结道，这些年轻人虽然业已成年
Ultimately saying that, despite having attained maturity,
却一个个骨瘦如柴
young men are naught but emaciated.
我的意思是，瞧瞧这家伙，他居然穿长筒袜
I mean, look at this guy, he's wearing stockings!
戴假发
A wig!
还化妆
Makeup!
他还骑马
He rides horses!
给里给气
Gayiiiii!
不可避免地，到了2040年，理查德大叔也会在圣诞晚宴上扫兴地说
Inevitably, Uncle Richard will ruin Christmas dinner in the twenty-forties by saying,
2010年代的生活可比现在好太多了
Life was so much better in the twenty-tens,
我们必须回归传统，那时候，婚姻是缔结在两个人类之间的
We must return to tradition when marriage was between two humans,
而不是像现在这些“机器人性恋”，毒害我们的孩子
not these robo-sexuals indoctrinating our kids.
我们现在都清楚，尽管有各种缺陷，现代生活还是优于以往任何时代
We all know by now that despite its flaws, modern life is superior to anything that came before, in nearly any single way.
既然如此，为什么我们有成千上万的老登在歌颂老黄油刀
In that case, why do we have literally thousands of old people celebrating old butter knives,
更有无数的年轻人在抱怨机械化农业呢，我想我找到答案了
and even more young people complaining about mechanised agriculture? I think I know why.
两德在34年前重新统一
The two Germanys reunited 34 years ago,
但那些曾在东德生活过的人，仍未放弃对旧共产主义制度的怀念
but those who lived in East Germany still haven't given up their nostalgia for the old communist system.
大多数东德人同意这个说法：
A majority of East Germans agree with the statement,
东德的好处多于坏处，虽然有些问题，但那里的生活挺好
East Germany had more good sides than bad sides, there were some problems, but life was good there.
然而与此同时，83%的东德人赞成向市场经济过渡
Yet at the same time, 83% of East Germans approved the transition to a market economy,
并且，从1990年到2019年，表示对生活“满意”的东德人数量
and the number of East Germans saying they are satisfied with their life
激增了44个百分点
increased by 44 percentage points from 1990 to 2019.
这又是怎么一回事呢？
What gives?
嗯，当被问及他们具体怀念东德的什么时
Well, when asked what they specifically missed about East Germany,
很少有受访者真正提到经济体制
very few respondents actually said the economic system,
或是共产主义政府
the communist government,
或是那个把每个人都变成偏执狂、互相监视邻居的“斯塔西”
or the Stasi turning everyone into paranoid freaks spying on their neighbours.
他们最怀念的，是那时的学校系统、独特的食物、公共艺术
What they missed the most was the school system, the unique food, the public art,
以及那种“大家都在为共同目标而奋斗”的感觉
the idea that they were all working towards a common goal,
即便那个目标实际上遥不可及
even if that goal wasn't actually getting any closer.
他们怀念的是那时一切的“简单纯粹”
They miss how simpler everything was back then.
东德人享受着过去的美学
East Germans enjoy the aesthetics of the past,
但他们中的大多数都承认，今天的生活更美好
but most of them recognise their lives are better today.
我想，这正是这种心态的核心，无论是要求恢复包办婚姻的极端保守派
I think that's at the core of this mindset, from the hyper-conservatives demanding a return to arranged marriages,
还是你家在Facebook上转发老式电话亭的奶奶
to your grandma sharing Facebook posts about phone boxes.
都会感觉现代生活似乎有点“素”，甚至可以说，有些寡淡无味
modern life can seem a little vegetarian, somewhat bland.
从建筑到邮筒，一切都被简化了
Everything from buildings to post boxes have been simplified,
从日常生活的斑斓画卷中，抹去了一些丰富的色彩
removing some of the richness from the tapestry of everyday life.
当一切都可以在线购买，所有人动动手指就能联系到
When everything can be bought online, and everyone can be contacted at an arm's reach,
你还有什么理由非得跑去酒吧社交
what reason do you have to go to socialise at the pub,
跟蔬果店老板唠嗑，或者干脆出门呢
gossip with the greengrocer, or go outside at all?
当在线追剧刷视频就能取代所有其他爱好时
When consuming media online can replace all other hobbies,
你还有什么理由去发展成一个“有趣”的人呢
what reason do you have to develop into an interesting person?
自然而然，这让人们变得非常孤单，也非常怨愤
Naturally, this makes people very lonely and very bitter.
回望过去，便很容易认为，逝去时光里的人们更快乐、更会社交
It's easy to look back and think people were happier and more sociable in days gone by.
如何扭转这一切，超出了本视频的讨论范围
How we can undo this is beyond the scope of this video,
所以，我将留给你们一段摘自日本古籍《叶隐》的文字
so I'll leave you with an extract from the Japanese book Hagakure.
故事讲述了一位诞生于和平年代的年轻武士
The narrative follows a young warrior born into an era of peace,
在武士间最后的大战结束几十年后才出生
born decades after the last great wars between the samurai.
他被无聊所困，渴望冲突重现，只为给自己的生命赋予意义
Plagued by boredom, he yearns for a return to conflict, solely to provide purpose in his life.
时代之风渐渐地滑向低俗
It is said that what is called the spirit of an age is something to which one cannot return.
译本来源：广西师范大学出版社《叶隐闻书》
是末世来临的证据
That this spirit gradually dissipates is due to the world's coming to an end.
想把当代恢复到百年前的良好风俗
For this reason, although one would like to change today's world back to the spirit of 100 years or more ago,
是不可能的
it cannot be done.
在哪个时代就做好哪个时代的事，这才是最重要的
Therefore, it is important to make the best out of every generation.
♪就算大雨滂沱又何妨♪
What does it matter if rain comes your way?
♪就算雨滴终日敲打♪
And raindrops pattern all day?
♪倾盆大雨也不该让你忧郁♪
The rain descending should not make you blue.
♪美好的结局正在前方等你♪
The happy ending is waiting for you.